The world makes you something that you're not,
العالم يجعلك تصبح شيئا مختلفا عما أنت عليه،
but you know inside what you are,
ولكن، في داخلك، أنت تعرف من أنت،
and that question burns in your heart:
وذلك السؤال يحترق داخلك:
How will you become that?
كيف تصبح كذلك؟
I may be somewhat unique in this,
ربما أكون فريدًة في ذلك،
but I am not alone,
ولكني لست وحيدًة،
not alone at all.
لست وحيدًة على الإطلاق.
So when I became a fashion model,
لذلك حين أصبحت عارضة أزياء،
I felt that I'd finally achieved the dream
أحسست بأني أخيرًا سأحقق الحلم
that I'd always wanted since I was a young child.
الذي طالما حلمت به منذ كنت طفلة.
My outside self finally matched my inner truth,
شخصيتي الخارجية تتطابق مع حقيقتي الداخلية.
my inner self.
مع ذاتي.
For complicated reasons which I'll get to later,
لعدة أسباب معقدة، سأتطرق لها لاحقًا،
when I look at this picture,
عندما أنظر إلى هذه الصورة،
at that time I felt like, Geena, you've done it,
حينها، شعرت بأني حققت ذلك.
you've made it,
لقد حققتي ذلك.
you have arrived.
لقد وصلتي.
But this past October,
ولكن خلال أكتوبر الماضي،
I realized that I'm only just beginning.
أدركت أني مازلت فقط في البداية.
All of us are put in boxes by our family,
جميعنًا، تم وضعنا داخل صناديق من قبل أهالينا،
by our religion,
بسبب الدين،
by our society,
بسبب المجتمع،
our moment in history,
بسبب لحظات من التاريخ.
even our own bodies.
حتى أجسامنا ذاتها.
Some people have the courage to break free,
بعض الأشخاص لديه الشجاعة لكسر ذلك،
not to accept the limitations imposed by
وعدم قبول الحدود المفروضة
the color of their skin
عليهم بسبب لون بشرتهم
or by the beliefs of those that surround them.
أو بسبب اعتقادات من حولهم.
Those people are always the threat
هؤلاء الأشخاص هو مصدر تهديد مستمر
to the status quo,
للوضع الراهن،
to what is considered acceptable.
لما يعتبر حاليًا مقبولًا.
In my case, for the last nine years,
في حالتي، خلال السنوات التسعة الماضية،
some of my neighbors,
بعض جيراني،
some of my friends, colleagues, even my agent,
بعض أصدقائي وزملائي وحتى وكيلي،
did not know about my history.
لم يعرفو عن تاريخي.
I think, in mystery, this is called the reveal.
أعتقد، بشكل غامض، هذا ما يسمى بالإفشاء.
Here is mine.
وهذا سري.
I was assigned boy at birth
لقد تم تسجيلي عند الولادة كصبي
based on the appearance of my genitalia.
استنادًا على الشكل الخارجي لأعضائي التناسلية.
I remember when I was five years old
أذكر حين كنت بعمر 5 سنوات
in the Philippines walking around our house,
في الفلبين، متجولًا حول المنزل،
I would always wear this t-shirt on my head.
كنت دائما أضع قميصا على رأسي.
And my mom asked me,
وكانت أمي تسالني،
"How come you always wear that t-shirt on your head?"
"كيف يمكنك ارتداء ذلك القميص على رأسك طوال الوقت؟"
I said, "Mom, this is my hair. I'm a girl."
كنت أقول: "ماما، هذا شعري، أنا فتاة."
I knew then how to self-identify.
عرفت حينها كيفية التعريف الذاتي.
Gender has always been considered a fact,
الجنس، كان ومازال يعتبر حقيقة مطلقة.
immutable,
غير قابلة للتغيير،
but we now know it's actually more fluid,
ولكننا نعرف الآن أنه أكثر مرونة،
complex and mysterious.
وتعقيدًا وغموضًا.
Because of my success, I never had the courage
بسبب نجاحي، لم أملك الشجاعة
to share my story,
لمشاركة قصتي،
not because I thought what I am is wrong,
ليس بسبب اعتقادي بأنني مخطئة،
but because of how the world treats those of us
ولكن بسبب كيفية تعامل العالم معنا.
who wish to break free.
والذي نتمنى أن نعيش بحرية.
Every day,
كل يوم،
I am so grateful because I am a woman.
أنا ممتنة جدًا بأنني امرأة.
I have a mom and dad and family
لدي أم وأب وعائلة
who accepted me for who I am.
الذين تقبلوا حقيقتي كما أود أن أكون.
Many are not so fortunate.
العديد ليسوا بذلك الحظ.
There's a long tradition in Asian culture
هناك عادة قديمة في الثقافة الآسيوية
that celebrates the fluid mystery of gender.
تحتفل بالغموض المائع للجنس.
There is a Buddhist goddess of compassion.
هناك آلهة بوذي للشفقة.
There is a Hindu goddess, hijra goddess.
هناك آلهة هندوسية، إلهة الهجرة.
So when I was eight years old,
وذلك حين كنت في الثامنة،
I was at a fiesta in the Philippines celebrating
كنت في احتفال في الفلبين
these mysteries.
بتلك الأسرار.
I was in front of the stage,
كنت في مقدمة المسرح،
and I remember, out comes this beautiful woman
وأتذكر، ظهرت تلك السيدة الجميلة
right in front of me,
أمامي تحديدًا،
and I remember that moment something hit me:
وأتذكر تلك اللحظة شيئًا ما داخلي يقول:
That is the kind of woman I would like to be.
هذا هو ما أريد أن أصبحه.
So when I was 15 years old,
لذك حين كنت في الخامسة عشر،
still dressing as a boy,
مازلت ألبس ثياب صبي،
I met this woman named T.L.
قابلت سيدة اسمها "تي.أل"
She is a transgender beauty pageant manager.
كانت مديرة لوكالة استعراض للمتحولين جنسيًا.
That night she asked me,
تلك الليلة سألتني،
"How come you are not joining the beauty pageant?"
"كيف لم تنضمي إلى مسابقات الجمال؟"
She convinced me that if I joined
لقد أقتنعتني أنه إذا أردت ذلك
that she would take care of the registration fee
بأنها ستتكلف برسوم التسجيل
and the garments,
والملابس،
and that night,
وتلك الليلة،
I won best in swimsuit
لقد ربحت في ملابس السباحة
and best in long gown
والافضل في الرداء الطويل
and placed second runner up
وأخذت المركز الثاني في المسابقة
among 40-plus candidates.
من بين 40 مشاركًة.
That moment changed my life.
تلك اللحظة غيرت حياتي.
All of a sudden, I was introduced
وفجأة، تم تقديمي
to the world of beauty pageants.
إلى مسابقة جمال العالم.
Not a lot of people could say that your first job
وليس معتادًا بأن تكون أول مهنة
is a pageant queen for transgender women,
هي ملكة جمال المتحولين جنسيًا،
but I'll take it.
ولكني اغتنمت الفرصة.
So from 15 to 17 years old, I joined
ولذلك من 15 سنة إلى 17 سنة
the most prestigious pageant
شاركت في معظم تلك المسابقات
to the pageant where it's at the back of the truck, literally,
حتى أنني شاركت في مسابقة كانت تقام في شاحنة قطر. حرفيًا.
or sometimes it would be a pavement next to a rice field,
أو في مرة أخرى، مسابقة كانت تقام بجانب حقل زراعة أرز،
and when it rains --
وحين تمطر -
it rains a lot in the Philippines --
وفي الفلبين تمطر بكثرة -
the organizers would have to move it
المنظم كان يضطر لنقل المسابقة
inside someone's house.
إلى داخل منزل أحد الأشخاص.
I also experienced the goodness of strangers,
لقد تعايشت مع طيبة الغرباء،
especially when we would travel
خصوصًا حين نسافر
in remote provinces in the Philippines.
إلى مقاطعات بعيدة في الفلبين.
But most importantly, I met
ولكن، الأهم في ذلك، أنني قابلت
some of my best friends in that community.
بعض أفضل أصدقائي من ذلك المجتمع.
In 2001,
في عام 2001،
my mom, who had moved to San Francisco,
والدتي، والتي انتقلت إلى سان فرانسيسكو،
called me and told me that my green card petition came through,
اتصلت بي وقالت انه تم الموافقة على طلب تصريح الدخول لأمريكا،
that I could now move to the United States.
والذي يعني تبعًا بأنه يمكنني الانتقال إلى أمريكا.
I resisted it.
لقد قاومت ذلك.
I told my mom, "Mom, I'm having fun.
أخبرت والدتي: "ماما، أنا مستمتعة
I'm here with my friends,
هنا مع أصدقائي،
I love traveling, being a beauty pageant queen."
أنا أحب السفر، وبكوني ملكة جمال."
But then two weeks later she called me, she said,
ولكن بعد أسبوعين، اتصلت وقالت:
"Did you know that if you move to the United States
"هل تعرفين أنه في أمريكا
you could change your name and gender marker?"
يمكنك تغيير اسمك وجنسك؟"
That was all I needed to hear.
ذلك كل ما احتجت سماعه.
My mom also told me to put two E's
أمي كذلك قالت لي بأن أضع حرف E مزدوج
in the spelling of my name.
في اسمي.
She also came with me when I had my surgery
وهي أيضًا كانت معي حين خضعت لعملية الجراحة
in Thailand at 19 years old.
في تايلند في عامي التاسع عشر.
It's interesting, in some of the most rural cities in Thailand,
ذلك مثير للعجب، حيث في بعض أفقر المدن في تايلند
they perform some of the most prestigious,
أدائهم يعتبر من أفضل وأدق
safe and sophisticated surgery.
وعلى مستوى عالي من الأمان في تلك العمليات الجراحية.
At that time in the United States,
حينها في الولايات المتحدة،
you needed to have surgery
يجب أن تخضع لجراحة
before you could change your name and gender marker.
قبل أن تقوم بتغيير الإسم والجنس المسجل.
So in 2001, I moved to San Francisco,
لذا، في عام 2001، انتقلت إلى سان فرانسيسكو،
and I remember looking at my California driver's license
وأتذكر حين كنت أريد الحصول على رخصة قيادة في كاليفورنيا
with the name Geena
وكان اسمي حينها Geena
and gender marker F.
وعلامة الجنس كانت "أنثى"
That was a powerful moment.
تلك كانت لحظة قوة.
For some people,
لبعض الناس،
their I.D. is their license to drive
الهوية الشخصية هي للقيادة
or even to get a drink,
أو حتى للحصول على كحول،
but for me, that was my license to live,
بالنسبة لي، كانت رخصتي للحياة،
to feel dignified.
لأشعر بالتبجيل.
All of a sudden, my fears were minimized.
وفجأة، شعوري بالخوف بدأ يذبل.
I felt that I could conquer my dream
شعرت بأني قادرة على تحقيق حلمي
and move to New York and be a model.
والانتقال للعيش في نيويورك كعارضة.
Many are not so fortunate.
العديد ليسو سعداء حظ.
I think of this woman named Islan Nettles.
أنا أعتقد أنه بسبب تلك المرأة والتي اسمها آيلا نيتلز.
She's from New York, she's a young woman
فهي من نيويورك، وهي سيدة يافعة
who was courageously living her truth,
كانت تعيش حقيقتها بشجاعة،
but hatred ended her life.
ولكن الكراهية تحيط بحياتها.
For most of my community,
وبالنسبة للغالبية في مجتمعي،
this is the reality in which we live.
هذه هي حقيقة حياتنا.
Our suicide rate is nine times higher
معدل الانتحار لدينا أعلى ب9 مرات
than that of the general population.
من المعدل العام.
Every November 20,
في ال20 من نوفمبر،
we have a global vigil
ننظم وقفة عالمية
for Transgender Day of Remembrance.
لذكرى يوم المتحولين.
I'm here at this stage
أنا هنا على هذا المسرح
because it's a long history of people who fought
بفضل تاريخ طويل لأولئك الناس الذين ناضلوا
and stood up for injustice.
ووقفوا ضد الظلم.
This is Marsha P. Johnson and Sylvia Rivera.
هذه هي مارشا بي وجونسون وسيلفيا ريفيرا.
Today, this very moment,
اليوم، وهذه اللحظة بالذات،
is my real coming out.
هذه هي لحظة ظهوري الحقيقية.
I could no longer live my truth
لم أعد أستطيع عيش حقيقتي
for and by myself.
من أجل نفسي ولوحدي فقط.
I want to do my best to help others
أود تقديم الأفضل لمساعدة الآخرين
live their truth without shame and terror.
ليعيشوا حياتهم بدون خجل أو خوف.
I am here, exposed,
أنا هنا، مكشوفة،
so that one day there will never be a need
حتى في يوم ما، لن تكون هناك حاجة
for a November 20 vigil.
لوقفة ال20 من نوفمبر.
My deepest truth allowed me to accept who I am.
حقيقتي الداخلية جعلتني أتقبل ذاتي.
Will you?
هل يمكنك ذلك؟
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلًا، شكرا جزيلًا. (تصفيق)
Kathryn Schulz: Geena, one quick question for you.
كاثرين شولز: جينا، سؤال سريع لك.
I'm wondering what you would say,
أنا أتسائل ماذا ستقولين،
especially to parents,
خصوصا للآباء،
but in a more broad way, to friends,
ولكن بشكل أوسع، للأصدقاء،
to family, to anyone who finds themselves
للعائلة، لأي شخص يجد نفسه
encountering a child or a person
في مواجهة مع طفل أو شخص
who is struggling with and uncomfortable with
يواجه أو يمر بوضع مربك
a gender that's being assigned them,
عن الجنس الذي تم تحديده له،
what might you say
ماذا يمكنك قوله
to the family members of that person
لعائلة ذلك الشخص
to help them become good and caring and kind
لمساعدتهم أن يصبحوا أفضل، مراعيين ولطفاء
family members to them?
بالنسبة لهم؟
Geena Rocero: Sure. Well, first, really, I'm so blessed.
جينا: بالطبع، حسنًا. بداية، أنا جد محظوظة.
The support system, with my mom especially,
نظام الدعم، خصوصا مع دعم والدتي،
and my family, that in itself
وعائلتي، بحد ذاته
is just so powerful.
كان قويًا جدًا.
I remember every time I would coach
أتذكر كل لحظة أود تدريب
young trans women, I would mentor them,
امرأة متحوله يافعة، أنصحهم،
and sometimes when they would call me
أو أحيانا حين يتصلون بي
and tell me that their parents can't accept it,
ويخبرونني بأن والديهم لا يقبلون ذلك.
I would pick up that phone call and tell my mom,
كنت أرفع الهاتف وأتصل بوالدتي،
"Mom, can you call this woman?"
" ماما، هل يمكنك التحدث مع تلك المرأة؟"
And sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn't, so —
وأحيانا يجدي نفعًا، وأحيانا لا ينفع.
But it's just, gender identity
ولكن ذلك فقط تحديد الجنس
is in the core of our being, right?
في صميمنا، أليس كذلك؟
I mean, we're all assigned gender at birth,
أعني، جميعنا تم تصنفينا حين ولدنا،
so what I'm trying to do
ولذلك ما أحاول القيام به
is to have this conversation that
هو بدء تلك المحادثة
sometimes that gender assignment doesn't match,
أنه أحيانا الجنس المحدد لنا لا يوافقنا.
and there should be a space
ولذلك يجب أن توجد مساحة
that would allow people to self-identify,
تمكن للناس تحديده ذاتيا،
and that's a conversation that we should have
وتلك المحادثة التي علينا خوضها يجب
with parents, with colleagues.
أن تكون مع الآباء، والزملاء.
The transgender movement,
حركة المتحولين جنسيًا،
it's at the very beginning,
مازالت في البداية،
to compare to how the gay movement started.
مقارنة مع كيف بدأت حركة المثليين.
There's still a lot of work that needs to be done.
مازال الكثير مما يجب عمله.
There should be an understanding.
يجب أن يكون هناك تفهم.
There should be a space of curiosity
يمكن أن توجد مساحه للتساؤل
and asking questions,
وطرح الأسئلة،
and I hope all of you guys will be my allies.
وأنا أتمنى منكم جميعًا أن تكونوا حلفائي.
KS: Thank you. That was so lovely. GR: Thank you.
كاثرين: شكرا جزيلًا، كان ذلك رائعًا. جينا: شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)